- 着火啦！ - 去拿水桶！
- Fire! - Get the buckets!
- 去海边取水！ - 怎么了？
- To the ocean! - What happened?
风向变了！ 救火小分队，前进！
The wind is shifting! Fire brigade, move in!
- 把南边的纳德龙带过来！ - 正在办！
- Bring the Nadders in from the south! - I'm on it!
葛伦科龙，瞄准屋顶！
Gronckles, aim for the roof!
干得好！ 只有几处着火点了
Good work! Just a few hot spots left.
- 明白！ - 高伯在哪？他仍在里面？
- Got it! - Where's Gobber? Is he still inside?
没，没发现他
No. Can't find him.
我在这
I'm right here.
那个怪兽将为此付出代价
That beast will pay for this.
高伯，出什么事了？
Gobber, what happened?
你觉得现在什么情况？ 一条龙把我家烧了
What's it look like? A dragon set my home on fire.
什么？
What?
你这次逼我太甚了，你这丑陋的大骨架！
You pushed me too far this time, you ugly bag of bones!
爸，他在说什么？ 我们的龙不会再那样做了
Dad, what's he talking about? Our dragons don't do that anymore.
他指的不是你的龙 高伯，我最后一次声明
He doesn't mean one of yours. Gobber, for the last time,
- 世界上从来不存在。。。 - 骨碎龙？
- there is no such thing as a... - Boneknapper?
骨碎龙……？
A boneknapper...?
什么碎来着？
What-knapper?
一种令人作呕、散发恶臭的怪物 披着一副偷抢来的骨头盔甲
A disgusting, foul beast, wearing a coat of stolen bones,
就像巨大的飞天骷髅
like a giant, flying skeleton.
恐龙手册上说骨碎龙永不停止地寻找
The dragon manual says that the Boneknapper will stop at nothing
完美的骨头来升级盔甲 太棒了
to find the perfect bone to build its coat of armor. It's awesome.
得了吧！这只是神话 这种龙根本不存在
Come on! It's a myth. It doesn't even exist.
我告诉你，这是千真万确的 我一生都在躲避它
I'm telling you, it's real. I've been running from him my whole life.
我房子着火也是拜它所赐
He's the one who started this fire.
斯托伊克，我们发现了高伯 挂在炉子上的内裤
Stoick, we found Gobber's underpants hanging by the stove.
着火的原因一定是这个
They must've started the fire.
你仍认为这事有关骨碎龙 还是说是你的内裤弄的？
You still think it's the Boneknapper, or just your underpants?
我才不想考虑这种简单问题！我清楚！ 终究，它还是找上我了
I don't think! I know! Somehow he found me again.
这种龙简直就像恶魔
This dragon is pure evil.
高伯，已经深夜了 我们对你的故事也厌烦了
Gobber, it's late and we're too tired for your stories.
现在，该休息了
Now, get some rest.
你休息吧，我得结束我和那条龙之间的恩怨
You rest. I'm putting an end to this.
走吧，菲尔，我们走
Come on, Phil, let's go.
反正我又不需要他们的帮助
I don't need their help, anyway.
我不能让他一个人去
I can't let him go by himself.
好了，维京人，拿起你的盾牌
All right, Vikings, grab your shields.
- 是！ - 是！
- Yes! - Yeah!
让我上船去找什么不存在的龙 没门
There's no way I'm getting on a boat to go after a fake dragon.
用力！往后仰，你们这些懒虫！ 快划！
Come on! Put your backs into it, you lazy dogs! Stroke!
- 你们都不用点力！划！ - 很有趣，是吧？
- You're not even trying! Stroke! - How fun is this? Right?
我们的队伍又聚在一起了 又是一场冒险……
We got the team back together, another adventure...
这相当酷，嘿？
This is pretty cool, huh?
是的，没什么比划船划到手流血更酷了
Yep, nothing cooler than rowing until your hands bleed.
我只想让你们这些孩子知道 它是我的心头之隐忧
Just want you kids to know that it touches my heart,
你们帮我宰了骨碎龙 你们就是真正的维京人
you helping me slay the Boneknapper. True Vikings, you are.
- 高伯，我们到了吗？ - 哦，近了我就会告诉你的
- Gobber, are we there yet? - Oh, you'll know we're close
这时你的耳边会传来刺耳的尖叫
when your ears explode from the piercing screams.
传说里说这种龙的咆哮威力相当强
Legend says this dragon's roar is so fierce,
可以令你骨肉分离
it can melt the flesh right off your bones.
不对，鱼腿
Not so, Fishlegs.
骨碎龙不会咆哮 这就是它可怕之处
The Boneknapper has no roar at all. That's why he's terrifying.
它是无声的杀手
He's a silent killer.
等等，如果我们没听到任何声音 我们就要死了？
Wait. So if we don't hear anything, we're dead?
我听不到任何声音
I don't hear anything.
干得好，菲尔！
Good one, Phil!
我以前没告诉过你们 我第一次遭遇令人闻风丧胆的骨碎龙时的情景？
Did I ever tell you about the first time I met the dreaded Boneknapper?
那时我还是个年轻的小伙，如你们这般年纪 和我的家人正在进行夏日假期旅行
I was a young lad, about your age, on summer vacation with my family,
中途我要小便
when I heard the call of nature.
哦！爸，停船！
Oh! Dad, pull the boat over!
我不是告诉你出发前就应该去了吗？
Didn't I tell ya to go before we left?
我看见了一个维京战队 在战斗中被冰封住了
I saw an army of Vikings, frozen in battle!
其中一名维京士兵手里紧紧握着
Clutched in the fingers of one of the Vikings
一个小宝盒 我想拿到它
was a small treasure chest. I had to have it.
我手伸进去，拿出宝盒
I reached in and pulled out the chest.
那是我见过的 最美丽的东西
It was the most beautiful thing I ever saw.
但冰冻的维京士兵仍然活着
But the frozen Viking was alive!
他打了我的脸几拳！
He started punching me in the face!
我的牙齿！
My tooth!
而它就在此刻现身了 消无声息
And there it was. >I never even heard it coming.
骨碎龙
The Boneknapper!
它撞向冰川 冻成冰块的维京士兵几乎形成了一场雪崩
It crashed into the glacier, causing an avalanche of frozen Vikings!
宝盒！
The treasure!
我把手伸入水中
I reached into the water...
再次招来冰冻维京士兵迎面几拳乱打
...only to find the frozen Viking punching me in the face again!
嘿
Hey, hey, hey, hey!
骨碎龙想要那宝盒 但我更想要
The Boneknapper wanted that treasure, but I wanted it more!
怎么去了那么久？
What took you so long?
你想让我们相信你被冰冻的维京士兵打了？
You expect us to believe that a frozen Viking punched you in the face?
是的，两次
Yeah, twice.
嘿，这种情况有可能发生
Hey, it could happen.
你什么意思“有可能”，这千真万确
What do you mean, "It could happen?" It did!
但我比那无声的怪兽更机灵
But I outsmarted the silent beast.
高伯，我本不想做一个纠结于细节的人
Gobber, I hate to be a stickler for details,
但骨碎龙并不是无声的
but Boneknappers are not silent.
鱼腿，我清楚的知道自己没有听到声音
Fishlegs, I know what I didn't hear.
- 但我可以感觉到…… - 伙计们？
- But I could feel it... - Guys?
- 这应该是？ - 对危险有第六感
- Are there supposed to be...? - ...had a sixth sense for danger.
- 我能嗅出任何东西 - 我们一定是撞上什么了……
- I can smell anything... - We're gonna hit these...
感受到将要发生的劫数
...taste the oncoming doom...
我只感觉到了石头
I'm tasting rocks.
我们到了
We're here.
现在，我们困在未知之所了
Now, we're stuck in the middle of nowhere
而且也没人知道我们在哪
and no one even knows where we are.
骨碎龙知道 传说中说……
Except the Boneknapper. Legend says...
嘿，你知道传说里还讲过什么？ 安静！
Hey, you know what legend also says? Stop talking!
- 好吧，那就等会再说 - 孩子们，没必要慌张
- OK, just hold on one darn second. - No need to panic, kids.
- 我都经历过好多次沉船了 - 哦，这确实让人欣慰
- I've been shipwrecked many times. - Well, that's comforting.
你永远不会忘记你的第一次沉船
You never forget your first shipwreck.
我搁浅在一个岛上 身边仅剩一把扫帚
I was stranded on an island with only my broom.
那是一个非常小的岛屿
It was a very small island.
被骨碎龙发现也就不足为奇了
It's no wonder the Boneknapper found me again.
它不会原谅我 拿走了那宝盒
He never forgave me for taking that treasure.
附近还有另一个岛 我唯一的逃生去处
There was another island, my only escape.
但是周围都是 嗜血的锤头鲨
But I was surrounded by bloodthirsty hammerhead sharks!
我只有一次机会
I only had one chance.
因此我径直冲过 遍布鲨鱼的海
So I ran across the shark-infested waters.
接着！看着！ 拜拜，胖子！
Take that! Watch it! Night-night, fatty!
有人忘了刷牙
Someone forgot to brush.
我并没料到自己会成功逃脱
I didn't think I was gonna make it.
但忽然间，从海里的深处跃出
But then, from the depths of the ocean, leapt forth
一只巨大的座头鲸
a giant hammerhead whale!
座头鲸把骨碎龙吃了？
And the hammerhead whale ate the Boneknapper?
差一点，它逃脱了
Almost, but he got away.
几年以后，骨碎龙再次找到我 把我追至丛林之中
Years later, the dragon hunted me down again and chased me into the jungle.
身上只剩下我深爱的打蛋器
All I had was my trusty egg beater.
我像山猫一样穿过茂密的丛林
I carved through that thick brush as fast as a jungle cat.
但是，骨碎龙仍然紧追不舍
Still, the Boneknapper was right behind!
杜鹃花！
Azaleas!
我顺着火山往上爬
I ran up the side of a volcano
并无畏地跃过炙热的火山口
and courageously leapt across the fiery crater.
就在那时，炙热的火山深处
Then, deep within the burning volcano,
喷出一头巨大的座头牛
burst forth a giant hammerhead yak!
好了，等下，你是在说一头巨大的座头牛
OK, wait a minute. Now you're saying a giant hammerhead yak
从火山里跳出来吃了骨碎龙？
leapt out of a fiery volcano and ate the Boneknapper?
你可能会这样认为，不是吗？ 但是骨碎龙再次逃脱了！
You would've thought so, wouldn't you? But the dragon got away again!
我就知道那恶棍会对我穷追不舍的
I knew that boney scoundrel would keep coming after me.
于是我准备了一个陷阱 守株待兔
So I set up a gauntlet of traps and waited for the beast.
然后它出现了
And when he was ready...
它直冲而来
...he charged!
我迅疾逃走
And then I ran like the wind!
但陷阱没成功
But the traps failed!
然后，我被逮住了
Then, captured,
我做了每个勇敢的维京人都会做的
I did what any brave Viking would do...
- 救命！ - 上帝一定听到我的祈祷了
- Help! - The gods must have heard my prayer.
托尔雷神
It was Thor!
它射出强大的霹雳
He tossed a mighty thunderbolt.
- 没击中 - 等一下……
- You missed! - Wait for it...
然后，从被砸中的大地中心窜出
Then, from the center of the earth, blasted forth...
一只骑在座头鲸上的座头牛
...the hammerhead yak riding the hammerhead whale!
发射
Deploy the yak.
太棒了！哦！我的背！
Yes! Oh, my back!
喔！鲸鱼救了你？
Whoa! The whale saluted you?
你们相信吗？ 骨碎龙再次消失了
Can you believe it? But the Boneknapper got away again.
- 它又找到我... - 你在开玩笑吧？
- He found me on... - Are you kidding?
- 我一点都不相信 - 全是你编造的
- I don't believe any of this. - You totally made everything up!
- 应该想法离开这里了 - 我们得回家
- It's time to get out of here. - We need to get home.
你连那东西存在的一点证据都没有
You don't even have any proof that that thing exists.
我当然有证据 我仍拥有那样宝物
Of course I have proof. I still have the treasure.
这了不起的带扣
This stunning belt buckle.
这是在维京人的宝盒里拿出的 别在我的裤带上已有几年了
It was in the Viking's treasure chest. It's kept my pants up for years.
- 这相当漂亮 - 听着，高伯
- It is stunning. - Listen, Gobber?
与其追踪一只臆想的龙
Instead of chasing down an imaginary dragon,
也许我们应该想想怎么回去
maybe we should figure out how to get home.
别多说了！我听得很清楚 我有个计划
Say no more! I hear you loud and clear. I've got a plan.
好了，谁想做骨碎龙的诱饵？
All right. Who'd like to be dragon bait?
高伯，你确信这样安全吗？
Gobber, are you sure this is safe?
可以说是万无一失
Safety's overrated.
好了，计划是这样的 骨碎龙要找我，对吧？
OK, here's the plan. The Boneknapper wants me, right?
它从那边过来，看到鱼腿 认为是我
He comes down that trail, sees Fishlegs, thinks it's me,
鱼腿的跑动让菲尔释放绳索
rushes Fishlegs, causing Phil to trip that rope,
投下那骨架笼子，然后我们过去一劳永逸地结果了它
dropping that ribcage and then we rush in and finish him off, once and for all!
他们变老时这么傻真是悲剧
It's sad when they get old.
高伯，你想的太多了，明白吗？
Gobber, you're taking this way too far, OK?
你得面对这个事实，世上没有骨碎龙这样的东西
You need to face it. There is no such thing as the Boneknapper.
趴着！现在，各就各位
Wormsquat! Now, get into position.
就是这样，鱼腿！ 你做得很好！
Way to go, Fishlegs! You're doing fine!
难怪村子里的人都认为你疯了
No wonder the entire village thinks you're crazy.
他看到的是一动不动的维京人
Hello? He sees dead Vikings.
- 是的，尤其是那…… - 伙计们？
- Yeah, especially that thing about... - Guys?
- 这是在浪费时间 - 伙计们！
- This is a waste of time. - Guys!
转身！伙计，伙计！
Turn around! Guys, guys!
什么？
What?
它就在我们身后，是吗？
It's right behind us, isn't it?
你知道什么？没咆哮的声音
Well, what do you know? No roar.
快跑！
Run!
好吧，高伯，我们信你了！
OK, Gobber, we believe you!
菲尔！
Phil!
选对了地方 选对了地方
Find a happy place, find a happy place.
不，不，别！别！
No, no, please! Please!
它想取我头！
He wants my head!
我发誓它想取我头！
I swear he wants my head!
来吧！等我出去了。。。
Bring it on! You wait till I get out there...
等会，它在寻找完美的骨头来建造它的盔甲
Wait. It searches for the perfect bone to build its coat of armor.
那宝物！ 高伯，脱下你的裤子
The treasure! Gobber, take off your pants.
- 不！ - 等会，听我说
- No! - Wait, listen to me.
我觉得鱼腿是对的
I think Fishlegs was right.
骨碎龙本会发出嚎叫
The Boneknapper is supposed to have a roar.
但它不能的原因可能是因为它要的骨头其实是你的带扣
But maybe he can't because the bone he needs is your belt buckle.
高伯，听我说 你得给它
Gobber, please, you have to give it back.
没门，这是我的！
No way. It's mine!
把骨头还给它！
Give him back his bone!
不行
No!
- 还给他！ - 不行
- Give him back his bone! - No!
不行……好吧！
No... All right.
高伯！
Gobber!
好吧，你抓住我了 快点杀了我
All right, you've got me. Make it fast.
这场景我会做噩梦的
That's gonna give me nightmares.
至少，我们有骑宠了
Well, at least we have a ride home.
你可爱吗？是的，你很可爱！ 很可爱
Aren't you cute? Yes, you are! Yes, you are.
好了
All right!
你知道，我从没怀疑他 我一直说的是，“他是对的”
You know, I never doubted him. I was always like, "He's right."
这尾骨真伤脊柱
This tailbone is hurting my tailbone.
它显然很高兴失落的骨头回来了
He sure seems happy to have that bone back.
传说骨碎龙的嚎叫是为了吸引异性
Well, legend says the Boneknapper's roar is its mating call.
哦，那只是个传说！
Oh, that's just a myth!
我想现在斯托伊克会相信我了，是吗？
I think Stoick will believe me now, eh?
字幕：朝闻道   QQ：12008834